Guide to the Blanche Thebom Collection ARS.0059
Archive of Recorded Sound
Blanche Thebom Collection
1934-2003
ARS.0059
Thebom, Blanche
85 boxes
Archive of Recorded Sound
The Blanche Thebom Collection has three major components. The first is scores, correspondence, publicity, production notes, and media from her post-Met career as teacher and director. Secondly, there are published and unpublished sound recordings of Thebom. Lastly, the collection also retains Thebom's extensive archive of printed music.
Access
Open for research; material must be requested at least two business days in advance of intended use. Contact the Archive for assistance.
Biography
Operatic mezzo-soprano Blanche Thebom was born in Monessen, Pennsylvania in 1915, and began her formal concert career in 1941. She was a member of the Metropolitan Opera through 1967, known for her roles in Wagnerian epics. During this period she also toured extensively, including being the first American to perform at the Bolshoi in Moscow. In 1967 she was appointed head of The Atlanta Opera Company in Atlanta, Georgia. Following that experience, Thebom taught at the University of Arkansas in Little Rock. In 1980 she moved to San Francisco and directed an opera workshop at San Francisco State University, and founded the Opera Arts Training Program in 1988 in conjunction with the San Francisco Girls Chorus. Thebom passed away in March 2010 at the age of 94.
Scope and Contents
The bulk of the Blanche Thebom Collection contains scores, publicity, correspondence, notes, and media from her many years as a theatrical director. Included are business records and production materials from the Atlanta Opera Company, production materials from the operas and puppet shows she directed at the University of Arkansas - Little Rock, and some files from her stint teaching at San Francisco State University. The largest portion of this collection is devoted to Thebom's own printed music collection, intact and in the order she kept it. Outside of some ephemera from her many tours abroad, there is little material from her time performing with the Metropolitan Opera, nor is there much in the way of personal correspondence. Thebom also did not keep a diary, nor did she intend to write a memoir. However, the collection does hold many recordings from this era, including test pressings from her years recording for RCA (some with unissued takes), as well as almost 150 unique recordings on fragile instantaneous discs, several from the 1930's.
Indexing Terms
Thebom, Blanche -- Archives; Atlanta Opera Company (Atlanta, Ga.).; University of Arkansas at Little Rock.; Mezzo-sopranos; Opera; Operas; Puppet theater
- Productions
  - Aida, 1967 (Box 34)
    Scope and Contents
    Verdi, Giuseppe, 1813-1901. Aïda.
  - Alice, 1976 (Box 4, Box 5, Box 6)
    An adaptation of Carroll's "Alice in Wonderland" for the stage by Thebom.
  - Amahl and The Night Visitors, 1975 (Box 2, Box 4, Box 5, Box 8)
    Menotti, Gian Carlo, 1911-2007. Amahl and the night visitors
  - The Astar Experiment, 1978 (Box 13, Box 46)
    Kirby, Lou Ann, 1948- Astar experiment
  - Barber of Seville, 1984 (Box 33)
    Rossini, Gioacchino, 1792-1868. Barbiere di Siviglia. Performed by the Marin Opera Company.
  - Bastien & Bastienne / Mozart Fete Galante, 1970-1976 (Box 3, Box 4)
    Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791. Bastien und Bastienne
  - La Bella Dormente (Box 4)
    Respighi, Ottorino, 1879-1936. Bella dormente nel bosco
  - Beret & Per Hanson, 1977-1978 (Box 5, Box 8, Box 13)
    Opera written by a Mr. Hagen, performed at UALR.
  - La Boheme (Box 34)
    Puccini, Giacomo, 1858-1924. Bohème. Photographs from the Atlanta performance.
  - Calhoun's Christmas, 1972-1980 (Box 5, Box 8, Box 9, Box 13)
    Palmer, Carleton. Calhoun's Christmas. Libretto by Thebom, adapted from the book by Phyllis McGimsey.
  - The Consul, 1974 (Box 13, Box 33)
    Menotti, Gian Carlo, 1911-2007. Consul
  - Carmen Cabaret / Caravan, 1971-1982 (Box 2, Box 4, Box 8, Box 14, Box 47)
    Bizet, Georges, 1838-1875. Carmen. Adapted as a condensed version by Thebom.
  - Childhood of Christ, 1977 (Box 5, Box 10, Box 11)
    Berlioz, Hector, 1803-1869. Enfance du Christ
  - Cinderella, 1979-1980 (Box 5, Box 6, Box 10)
    Rossini, Gioacchino, 1792-1868. Cenerentola (Cinderella). Thebom's final production at UALR.
  - Cosi Fan Tutte, 1975-1979 (Box 4, Box 17, Box 18, Box 33)
    Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791. Così fan tutte
  - The Devil And Daniel Webster, 1975-1982 (Box 15, Box 16)
    Benét, Stephen Vincent, 1898-1943. Devil and Daniel Webster
  - Don Quixote, 1978 (Box 1, Box 4, Box 5, Box 8)
    Massenet, Jules, 1842-1912. Don Quichotte
  - Holiday For Santa, 1970 (Box 3, Box 16)
    Thebom, Blanche. Holiday for Santa.
  - King Arthur, 1968 (Box 33, Box 34)
    Purcell, Henry, 1659-1695. King Arthur. Debut performance at Atlanta's Memorial Arts Center.
  - Les Mamelles de Tiresias, 1974 (Box 13, Box 16)
    Poulenc, Francis, 1899-1963. Mamelles de Tirésias
  - The Telephone (Box 13)
    Menotti, Gian Carlo, 1911-2007. Telephone
  - Master Pete's Puppet Show (Box 5)
    Falla, Manuel de, 1876-1946. Retablo de Maese Pedro
  - Merry Wives of Windsor, 1985 (Box 42, Box 47)
    Nicolai, Otto, 1810-1849. Lustigen Weiber von Windsor. Performed at San Francisco State.
  - The Old Maid And The Thief, 1978 (Box 4, Box 5, Box 8, Box 12)
    Menotti, Gian Carlo, 1911-2007. Old maid and the thief
  - Orfeo, 1974 (Box 4, Box 8, Box 9)
    Monteverdi, Claudio, 1567-1643. Orfeo
  - Snowmaiden, 1970 (Box 3, Box 5, Box 46)
    Rimsky-Korsakov, Nikolay, 1844-1908. Snegurochka
  - La Vida Breve (Box 5)
    Falla, Manuel de, 1876-1946. Vida breve
- Atlanta Opera Company / Atlanta Opera Council, 1960-1972; 2 boxes (Box 34, Box 47)
  Scope and contents
  Clippings, contracts, correspondence, memoranda, photographs, press releases, production notes, programs, Box recordings of gala, etc.
- Blanche Thebom Show, 1965; Twenty-five 7" open reel tapes (Box 16)
  Recordings from Thebom's interview program (also possibly titled "Blanche Thebom Presents..."). Guests: Robert Merrill, Gary Graffman, Edward Woodward, Nicolai Gedda, Dore Schave, Marian Anderson, Enoch Light, Andre Kostelanetz, Skitch Henderson, Giorgio Tozzi, Mitch Miller, Hildegarde, Roddy McDowell, Eleanor Stebes, Jerome Hines, Richard Tucker, Jan Mitchell, Mischa Ellman, Roberta Peters, Alicia Markova, Eileen Farrell, and Bill Cosby.
- Discs - Instantaneous, 149 instantaneous disc(s) One 7" disc; three 10" discs; one-hundred-and-forty-five 12" discs (Box 30, Box 44, Box 45)
- Discs - Commercially pressed shellac, Seventy 78 rpm discs (Box 7, Box 26)
- Dubrovnick Summer Festival, 1959; 2 boxes (Box 1, Box 33)
  Program and other ephemera from a festival in Croatia at which Thebom performed.
- Metropolitan Opera House demolition clippings, 1966-1967; 1 folder (Box 1)
- Printed music collection, circa 1934-2003; 19 boxes (Box 15, Box 19, Box 20, Box 21, Box 22, Box 23, Box 24, Box 27, Box 28, Box 29, Box 31, Box 32, Box 36, Box 37, Box 38, Box 39, Box 40, Box 41, Box 42)
  Published scores, libretti, sheet music, teaching guides, etc. Many signed or possibly notated by Thebom. Some are manuscripts and some are photocopies. There are folders grouped by subject such as "Russian", "Italian", "German", "Light English" and "Encore Material."
- Osaka International Festival, 1961; 2 boxes (Box 1, Box 33)
  Programs, scrapbook, and other ephemera from a festival in Japan at which Thebom performed.
- Songs of Experience - Daniel Steven Crafts, 1 score (Box 34)
  Crafts, Daniel Steven. Songs of Experience. Includes short correspondence and a news clipping.
- University of Arkansas at Little Rock (UALR), circa 1973-1980; 11 boxes (Box 1, Box 2, Box 3, Box 6, Box 10, Box 11, Box 12, Box 13, Box 14, Box 15, Box 18)
- UALR galas, 1969-1971; 2 boxes (Box 5, Box 13)
- Books, circa 1934-2003; 2 boxes (Box 25, Box 42)
  Books signed by or inscribed to Thebom. Some are signed by author. One book includes an essay ("Opera - Evolution or Revolution") by Thebom.
- Printed opera programs (San Francisco, Santa Fe, Seattle, Metropolitan), 1963-1990; 1 box (Box 25)
- Programs, clippings, correspondence, and personal documents, circa 1934-2003; 15 boxes; Villec, Phyllis (Box 1, Box 69, Box 70, Box 71, Box 74, Box 76, Box 77, Box 78, Box 79, Box 80, Box 81, Box 82, Box 83, Box 84, Box 85)
  Donor note
  Much of this series was donated by Villec, Phyllis, in 2014.
  Arrangement
  This series has been boxed in the order it was received. Its contents are therefore mostly unorganized at present.
  Sensitive material
  This series has not been weeded for potentially sensitive items. Researchers viewing these materials will therefore be required to sign an agreement that they will not disclose or reproduce any sensitive information they might find.
- Audiovisual material, 1938-1996; 6 boxes (Box 9, Box 16, Box 33, Box 46, Box 47)
  Many unmarked or poorly marked, some with no Thebom content. Among the recordings: Antony and Cleopatra 1966; Manila 1959; Kolodin; Trigere; "phone negotiations"; Samson and Delilah; Queen of Spades; Regina; Thebom interview KKHI; Thebom interview 1993 (also transferred to DVD); Aida 1953; The Trojans in London; many reels of disc transfers (marked with Roman numerals).
- Film, circa 1934-2003; 3 films One 1" film in 5" can; two 1/2" films in 12" cans (Box 17)
  Films are minimally marked. One says "In Brasil with Senador Church" on its can, another says "rehearsals" on its leader.
- Photographs and negatives, circa 1934-2003; 3 boxes; Villec, Phyllis (Box 72, Box 73, Box 75)